Guide to the Danbury Preservation Trust Records MS 039
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series I: Administration
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1983 DNT, NYT Clippings (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Articles regarding Union Carbide - NYT articles on move, downtown, Main St.
    - 1984 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Articles on the redevelopment tract appraisal, Errichetti proposal, Ives. St., regional mall, Rawlins house, Erichetti and Nolan bids, Harriet White Starr, Isaac Ives, Liberty St. Church and a Lowell Massachusetts article.
    - 1985 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Articles on Hearthstone Castle, the Nolan and Errichetti bids, Rowland tour of renovation Projects
    - 1986 - 1989 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Articles relating to redevelopment,, Main St. proposal, 13 Farview Ave, DPT article, Ives House, Ericson House and an article on the Pittsburgh railroad station
    - 1992, 1995 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Articles on Still River, Danbury Crossroads, the flood, Union Station and copy of DNT supplement
    - 1996 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Articles on Still River, Danbury flood, Savings Bank of Danbury redesign
    - Redevelopment related DNT clippings, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
      Articles regarding Danbury redevelopment
    - 1963 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
      Articles related to Main St., Still River Projects, Renewal, Housing Code, River St.
    - 1967 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
      Articles about WCSC purchase of Gregory farm, Farber sale of mall, Redevelopment, appraisals, GNRP - Greater Neighborhood Renewal Program
    - 1979 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
      Articles relating to - Danbury Downtown Council, Ives St. firehouse; Morris St. School, Main St. historic buildings and revitalization, Preservation Trust, Trust lectures, supermalls, regional mall, Palace Theater and copy of Hartford Architecture Conservancy publication
    - 1980 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
      Articles relating to Main St. revitalization, proposed downtown complex, Old Jail, Union Carbide, corporate development, downtown mall proposal, Walking tours, Baldwin photo exhibit, Ives St, Southeast mall, DPT grant, DPT donation.
    - 1981 Danbury News-Times clippings (Box 1, Folder 39-41)
      Articles on Preservation Day, "Economics of Amenity", Main St. Historic District, Oil Mill Road condos, old jail, walking tour, call to dump Errichetti, old library, Danbury Fair mall, housing
  - Operational
    - Materials re: Danbury Downtown Council, Jun 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7.1)
      Articles on preservation day, 'Economics of Amenity", Main St. Historic district, Oil Mill Rd. condos, old jail, walking tour, call to dump Errichetti, old library, Danbury Fair mall, housing
    - Rehabilitation assistance request correspondence, Jun 1905-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Meeting minutes, budgets, DNT articles, correspondence
    - IRS correspondence regarding Tax exempt status, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Requests for rehabilitation assistance to City of Danbury, for review by DPT
    - Material relating to Certificate of Incorporation, By-laws, 1979-1996 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Community Development Program, City of Danbury grants, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Correspondence from Community Development Program, Danbury Downtown Council to CDP, HUD grant - facades, surveys
    - Materials pertaining to tax exempt application, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
      501(c)(3) application, notes on budgets 1980-1982, Renews v.3 #4, Purpose of DPT paper, Minutes of Board Meeting, 9/7/82, EIN number document, status correspondence, copy of Downtown Council of New Haven application from 1979
    - DPT lease of Old Library space, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Federal Income Tax, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      1995 income tax forms,
    - Fundraising, grant and loan information, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      1988 list of Events, 1980 letter to Lowell Weicker, National Trust for Historic Preservation letter about grant and loan programs, CT Trust for Historic Preservation funds list, 2 National Trust pamphlets
    - History and purpose DPT documents, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letterhead statonary and certificate of merit forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Membership - miscellaneous materials, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Letters from DPT President etc. regarding membership, National Historic Register article about Connecticut Preservation Trust, membership flyers
    - Public hearing testimony materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Block grant request defense, Parks property, Main St., city housing court proposal
    - Speakers background & correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Correspondence with speakers, Portland Maine mayor, Market Street Restoration Agency of Corning NY, Economics of Amenity note, Norman Mintz, WCSC proposal for history course, John Mesick lecture and talk
    - Resumes, 1978-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Job applicants??
    - Correspondence and miscelaneous articles and papers, 1978-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Correspondence, newspaper articles, position papers, histories of the organization
    - Insurance policies, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
    - Office supplies, undated (Box OS 1, Folder *)
      Rolodex - petite, Index address cards, DPT roll of stickers, DPT paid stamp, DPT seal
    - Historic Resources Inventory, Building and Structure Forms, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Tax deferral assessment program correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      113 Mill Plain Rd. - tax deferral assesment
  - Research and Background Materials
    - City of Danbury Annual Report, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - CityCenter Danbury, 1988-1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Citycenter Danbury, activities
    - Connecticut Historic Restoration Fund Guidelines, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Connecticut Historical Commission publication
    - Connecticut Historical Commission miscellaneous materials, 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Commission announcements concerning the National Register of Historic Places, grants programs
    - Connecticut Preservation Action correspondence and reports, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Connecticut Preservation action - annual report, corrrespondence to DPT, copy of Action Alert for Apr 1986.
    - Danbury builders, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Biographies of old Danbury builders - Starr family,Gregory,Jarvis Polly, George Raymond
    - Danbury Museum and Historical Society, 1969-1991 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Scott Fanton calendar - 1991; paper on charter oak relic and explanation of McLeans coming to Danbury after 1869 flood.
    - Danbury historic panoramic views, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
      5 historic views of sections of Danbury with commentary
    - Connecticut Historical Commission programs and manuals, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
      Connecticut State Historic Preservation Office, 1984 Grants Manual - National Park Service Historic Preservation Program; booklet "Historic Preservation: a Cultural Resource Management Plan for Connecticut", Historical American Engineering Record (HAER)1990 updates
    - Connecticut Historic Preservation News, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 44-48)
      Copies of the publication of the Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation (with gaps)
    - Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation correspondence and materials, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 49-52)
      Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation - literature, list of consultants, correspondence re: meetings; Preservation for the Property owner news releases; Profiles of local preservation organizations
    - Cultural Development Plan for Western Connecticut, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 53-54)
      Greater Danbury Arts Council memos, history of cultural development plan, Cultural Development Plan for Western Connecticut, 1983 (2 copies)
    - Minority and Women in Business directories, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Directories published by Connecticut Dept of Economic Development sent by State Historic Preservation Officer
    - Preservation Action information, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Preservation Action, Washington D.C., materials, copies of 1986 Alert publication
    - Urban Renewal conferences miscellaneous materials, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Northeastern CT materials, NE Historical. Association conference schedule, book review, brochures - National Trust 1979, Main St. Revitalization Conference, Boston
    - The Prospects for Urban Revival excerpts, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Excerpts from paper titled "The prospects for urban revival" by Fossett and Nathan
    - William Bulkeley, Danbury News-Times, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
      William Bulkeley picture from DNT article, 2 pictures of office furniture from William Bulkeley's office
    - Historic Preservation organizations, 1983-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      Miscellaneous materials - locations in Conn 1983- 1989 and elsewhere 1994 -1996
    - Laws, regs. and ordinances, 1981-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
      2 copies of Connecticut P.A. 84-286; Bethel demolition ordinances; Danbury Ordinances regarding preservation and rehabilitation, Assessment deferral program; Misc. -handwritten notes, papers written on Historic preservation law
    - National Main Street Center, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
      Information on downtown revitalization produced by the National Main Street Center, part of the National Trust for Historic Preservation
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation materials, 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
      Micellaneous materials distributed by the National Trust for Historic Preservation
    - Urban Renewal in Michigan, Maine, Maryland, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
      Grand Rapids Art Museum in Historic Federal Building, Michigan; Portland Me. Golden Triangle Competition packet; Rockville MD. Town Center newsletter 1979 - 1980
    - The Specialist, 1994 (Box 9, Folder *)
      VHS tape from Connecticut Public Television - 25 min.
    - Center for Connecticut Studies (ECSU) booklets, 1975 (Box 9, Folder *)
      5 booklets: Puritans against the Wilderness by Van Dusen, From Revolution to Constitution by Roth and Meyer, A Diverse People by Trecker, Preachers Rebels and Traderby Andersen, From Yankee to American by Janick
    - Danbury Tricentennial Committee historic booklet series, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder *)
      5 booklets in case, Danbury History Series: Two centuries of hat making, how Danbury got to be what it is, Names - Places, The Untold Story, Danbury Tricentennial Committee
    - Oral history interviews, 1982-1995 (Box 9, Folder *)
      4 Standard cassette tapes: Mrs. A. Hoyt 17 Montgomery, Abe Najamy, Bert ? Regarding Danbury urban planning, Still River rechannelization; one with unreadable label - Bill ?
    - Slides of buildings throughout Danbury, 1979-1996 (Box 10, Folder *)
      Approx. 680 slides. Tray 1 Tabs: Balmforth Ave., Barnum Ct, Boughton, Beaver; Deer Hill; Farview, Franklin; Garfield, George; Great Palin, Stadley Rough; Ives St. Lake Ave.; Library Pl.; Liberty; Main St. details; Long Ridge, Starrs Plain; Main Downtown; Main St. Historic District; Main St. Streetscapes; Main St. south of St. Peter; Main north of News-TImes; Spring St.; Maple, Montgomery, Mountainville; New, NIchols, North; Orchard, Osborne, Oil Mill; Patch, Pearl, Pleasant; Stevens, Smith, South; Tarrywile and Hearthstone; Town Hill Ave; West, Washington, W. Wooster, Wooster, Westville; White St; 1981 walking tour - Old Jail plaque ceremony. Tray 2 tabs: houses; streetscapes; factories and warehouses; commercial; institution; people; Miscellaneous ;Feinson's; Still RIver Exhibit.
    - Laws, regs. and ordinances, 1984 (Box OS 1, Folder 2)
      Preservation Law Hartford Common Council regulations.
    - American Historical Review, 1996 (Box OS 1, Folder 15)
      The American Historical Review v.+E2:F17101 #4 10/1996
    - Danbury maps, undated (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder 1)
      Danbury, Main Street and Deer Hill Avenue Maps - topographic and street
    - Danbury flood articles, 1955 (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder 2)
      DNT pages 8/20/1955 Still River recedes; DNT pages 10/18/1955 Flood Protection; DNT pages 10/19/1955 Second flood victim
    - Mountainville Ave. and Frank Clark House postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Mountainville postcard, oldest house -Frank Clark house postcard
    - House photo, undated (Box OS 1, Folder 18)
      Color, 8x 10 photo of a green house, no address
    - National Register of Historic Places matierials, 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Informational materials from the National Register of Historic Places
    - Danbury Planning Commission Hearing Agendas, 1979-2001 (Box 2, Folder 58-61)
      Planning Commission Hearing agendas 1985, 1995-1997, 2000-2001 handwritten notes on 4/18/1979 meeting
    - Small Town Sourcebook, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
      Sourcebook published by Old Sturbridge Village
- Series II: Events
  - A Taste of Danbury
    - Taste of Danbury materials, 1987-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Co-sponsor of event with Danbury Downtown Council, Folder contains correspondence, picture of DPT display, copy of DNT article
    - Taste of Danbury - DNT pages, 1987 (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder 2)
      DNT pages 9/1/1987 Taste of Danbury,
  - Benefits and Awards
    - Honors Receptions, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Honors designation with plaques, honors reception booklents, noteworthy buildings
    - Tarrywile Benefit Fashion Show, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      DNT article on DPT high tea and fashion show at Tarrywhile to benefit Tarrywhile 1988
    - Collins Memorial Scholarship, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
      Essays, correspondence with schools, contestants, pictures of Steven Collins, notes on creation of scholarship award
    - Danbury Preservation Trust Annual Dinners, 1984-1997 (Box 3, Folder 29-36)
      correspondence, notes, booklets, - scholarship notes, 1986 Herb Janick picture, items for Annual Dinners mock-up program, purpose of trust document, committee members list, Parks property, Collins memorial scholarship notes, DPT slide show program 1986, Music guild building pictures, Sunderland Award, 1997 Palace Theater agenda
    - Civic Awards guest book, 1990 (Box OS 1, Folder 19)
      Civic Awards Ceremony guest book 3/25/1990
    - Proclamations, 1979-1988 (Box OS 1, Folder 20)
      City of Danbury, Mayor's Proclamations Danbury Preservation Week - 1979, 1988
  - Conferences
    - Mayor's Conference on Historic Preservation, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
      Articles on preservation, Mayor Dyer letter of welcome for conference, copies of DPT flyer, Herb Janick President's letter, action plan for downtown organization
    - Real Estate and Historic Properties Conference, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 43-47)
      Conference materials, Danbury Assessment deferral materials, 1989 conference materials, historic resources inventories for 52 Deer Hill and 95 Elm St.
    - Real Estate and Historic Properties Conference audio tapes, 1986 (Box 9, Folder *)
      4 standard cassette tapes labeled: DPT Real Estate Conference, Jerry Lombardi
  - Exhibits
    - "A River Runs Through It" - correspondence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Connecticut Tourism Manual, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      Connecticut Tourism Resource Manual 1996
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Exhibit booklet, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      3 copies of booklet for A River Runs Through It exhibit
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Connecticut Humanities Council, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 57-60)
      Connecticut Humanities Council funding, grant application
    - "A River Runs Through It"- guest book, 1974-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Guest book for the exhibit
    - "A River Runs Through It"- Danbury Redevelopment Agency history, 1974-1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "A River Runs Through It" - exhibit catalog and notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Copy for exhibit catalog, handwritten notes, 9/1/95 updated summary, Exhbit reception proposal
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Danbury Green, Still River materials, 1965-1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Danbury Green - materials on the Redevelopment Authority, copies of DNT articles on Still River
    - "A River Runs Through It" - urban renewal plan, 1963-1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Urban renewal plan - mid-town east neighborhood Apr. 1970, official land records copy Aug, 18, 1978
    - "A River Runs Through It" - exhibit flyers, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "A River Runs Through It" -photographs of 1955 flood (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Flood pictures (in sleeves) taken by Carol Troy
    - "A River Runs Through It" - oral history interviews information, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      Lists of people for oral history interviews on 1955 flood, letter proposing video of exhibit for 1997 Oral History Association nonprint format award
    - "A River Runs Through It" - negatives of sterioscope images, drawing, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
      4 negatives of sterioscope images, 1 negative of picture of artist's drawing
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Danbury postcards, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
      8 old postcards - Oilmill Pond, Still River near White St., Kenosha, one with message dated 1909 (******to be scanned)
    - "A River Runs Through It"- men studying map photographs and negative -, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
      2 prints and negative - 2 people looking at Still River, Brookfield map
    - "A River Runs Through It" Still River negatives, undated-1996 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Two negatives, Still River at low and high water
    - Roger Baldwin Main Street photos exhibit, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      Roger Baldwin, photographer of Main St. buildings, exhibit at Danbury Library
    - "A River Runs Through It"- background materials, 1939-1997 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
      DNT article, copy of US Army Corps Engineers pamphlet on Still River Projects, copies of pages from A Nation of Cities; material on Pittsburgh flood; maps, flood urban renewal Projects, color picture of railroad yard area
    - "A River Runs Through It" - project updates, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
      Exhibit project updates, schedule, report, memo exhibit story line, booklet format, student-faculty collaborative, commemorative DNT page; oral history list, copy of DNT articles, invoices, Danbury Sewage treatment plant materials; cleanup picture
    - "A River Runs Through It"- Danbury redevelopment timeline, 1962-1996 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
      History of Danbury redevelopment with timelines - Still River area, DNT articles on redevelopment area, handwritten notes
    - "A River Runs Through It"- Still River revitalization, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
      Still River Alliance revitalization booklet pages, maps correspondence; video script, Danbury sewage treatment plant information
    - "A River Runs Through It" -grant proposals, correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16-18)
      Grant proposals to Meserve memorial Fund and Danbury Cultural Commission, correspondence regarding exhibit, invoices, exhibit expenses
    - "A River Runs Through It" -photographs of Still River rechannelization, 1962-1971 (Box 4, Folder 23-26)
      photos of Still River downtown channelization Projects, laminated 1-51
    - "A River Runs Through It" -photographs of Barden flood damage and cleanup, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 27-31)
      Barden before and after cleanup - laminated photos and negatives
    - "A River Runs Through It"-photocopies of pictures -flood, river, downtown, undated-1996 (Box 4, Folder 36-44)
      Photocopies of pictures of: maps, 1955 flood pictures, rechannelization, Barden flood & cleanup, postcards - Kenosha, Oil Mill Pond, Beaverbrook; old Danbury & White's Pond; Main, White and Elm Sts.; White St. buildings demolition; tenement pictures
    - "A River Runs Through It"- photographs of the exhibit & negatives, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
      Pictures in envelopes of A River Runs Through It exhibit, 20 color photos in envelopes; negaives in 2 glassine holders
    - "A River Runs Through It"- Still River photographs, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 49-50)
      Still River photos - 1996: river, people fishing, boating, DPT members ?, 23 color photos in envelopes (1 empty) and 21 photos in second folder
    - "A River Runs Through It" - Danbury buildings & structures photographs, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 51-53)
      Photos - Superior Court building, Railway museum & train yard,, 26 color photos in envelopes; Ives St., Liberty Terrace, Patriot Manor, Patriot Garage, WCSU parking garage 21 color photos in envelopes; Main St. Galleria, Stew Leonard's, DPT members, Main St., Congregational Church, Danbury Mall 26 color photos in envelopes
    - "A River Runs Through It" - photos for Harmony and Banishment sections of exhibit, 1962-1996 (Box 4, Folder 54-56)
      Still River, Danbury photographs with negatives in envelopes; Danbury photos c. 1962 for "harmony" & "banishment" sections of exhibit 7 photos in envelope; sPhotos for "harmony" section of exhibit 7 photos in envelopes (8 X 10's )
    - "A River Runs Through It"Still River and surroundings - negatives and photos, 1950-1996 (Box 4, Folder 57-59)
      Still River near factories (DNT photo) - Color photo in envelope; Negatives of Still River photos,before and after flood views, pollution 9 large negatives in envelopes; negatives of Sanborn map sections, Von Gal Co,, Sewage Treatment Plant, White & Bridge St., Elm St., Still River (Beaverbrook), old Railroad Depot
    - Tenth Anniversary exhibit -The Preservationists, 1988-1988 (Box 4, Folder 61-62)
      Program booklet - 10th anniversary exhibit, The Preservationists at the Scott- Fanton Museum, correspondence with advertisers, sponsors, 17 3x5 pictures in indvidual envelopes
    - The Danbury Preservationists exhibit, Danbury Tricentennial information, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Danbury Tricentennial exhibit program, Danbury Preservationists, Sept. to Dec. 1984, calendars of events for Tricentennial 1984, 1985.
    - Roger Baldwin Main Street photos exhibit, 1980 (Oversized folder 3)
      Main Street: An Interpretation of Danbury's Architecture poster with (original pictures glued on)
    - Meeker's Hardware Centennial, 1983 (Box OS 1, Folder 14)
      Meeker's Hardware Centennial Anniversary - DNT page glued to board
    - "A River Runs Through It" - DNT articles, 1996 (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder 2)
      DNT Sunday magazine 6/2/1996 Still river exhibit; DNT reprint of flood articles 10/19/1955, 8/19/1955 (reprint 1996)
    - Future of the Past newspaper supplement and cable TV program, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Lists of expenditures, correspondence with ed. Of Historic Preservation re. The Future of the Past, Connecticut Humanities Council Grant 1980 - expenditures reports; CHC fund grantline from 1996
    - Scott Fanton Museum "Portuguese Culture in Danbury", undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
      Program and Protuguese community history notes
    - "The Mystique of the Home Front Sacrifice", 1993-1998 (Box 3, Folder 49-54)
      Connecticut Humanities Council Grant application, Connecticut Humanities issue Fall 1984 - Homefront article, Danbury Cultural Com. Grant application, Boland letter to Musuem board, timelines, lists of artifacts for exhibit, 50 photos in 5 envelopes with negatives, DNT articles (originals and copies), 2 articles on homefront, flyer for exhibit, 4 copies exhibit catalog
    - 1984 museum exhibit text (Box OS 1, Folder 4)
      Museum Exhibit, (exhibit text on boards )
    - Future of the Past newspaper supplement, 1983 (Map-case OS Drawer 3, Folder 2)